A lot of people they they have these
turning points where they lose a job or
they get divorced or maybe they have to
go to rehab for 6 months and they feel
like they're stuck.
What's your message to them based on
what you learned about your own journey?
Yeah, you're you're actually not stuck.
It feels like it, but things really do
get better. They really do.
You know, let me tell you a story, too.
Have you ever heard of the folk singer
Pete Seeger?
You you have. You have. You just don't
know it.
All the songs from our our youth that we
learned in kindergarten, those were all
Pete Seeger songs. Anyway,
um Pete told me a story one time about
the folk singer Phil Ochs. Phil Ochs was
huge in the '60s and '70s.
Phil um
Phil was
on a tour of Africa
to sing and put on concerts and he got
mugged.
And the mugger cut his cut his throat.
And he lived, but he was no longer able
to sing high notes.
And he went into a deep depression.
One night Pete was performing at the
Cafe Wha? in Greenwich Village.
And he had to literally run to Grand
Central Station to catch the last train
to Beacon, New York, which is where he
lived. It was the last train of the
night. So, just as he's packing up his
banjo and he's going to physically run
to Grand Central,
Phil Ochs calls and one of the
waitresses says, "Pete, Phil Ochs is on
the phone for you." And he grabs the
phone, he said, "Phil, I can't talk.
I've got to run and catch the last train
to Beacon." And he he said, "Call me
tomorrow." And he hung up.
And Phil Ochs killed himself.
He wanted to be talked out of it.
And Pete said,
"That selfish prick." He said, "I'll
never forgive him.
He had no idea how much he was hurting
the people who meant the most to him.
So, you know, when you're feeling at
your lowest,
like you're never going to claw your way
out of this, first of all, that's just
simply not true.
It really does get better.
But,
you have no idea
how loved you are
and how much you would hurt
the people that you care about the most.
I had a friend, James.
James did some really stupid when he was
young,
and he ended up
he ended up doing a 17 years of a
20-year sentence.
And
I mean, it's hard enough to get a job
when you you've got a a felony
conviction. If you have a violent felony
conviction,
you're never going to work, not in any
meaningful way.
And so, he went overseas.
Uh he was really ripped. He used to he
used to lift every day, so he went into
porn for a while, and he just he things
just weren't working out for him.
And he decided that he was going to
commit suicide, but he didn't want to
make a mess in his mother's house. So,
he took a gun, he drove to a Walmart
parking lot to kill himself. And just as
he puts the gun into his mouth,
an off-duty ATF agent pulls into the
next space. He just finished his shift,
and he's going to go into Walmart to do
his grocery shopping.
Pulls out his gun. Drop the gun. Drop
the gun.
James says, "You don't understand. I'm
I'm going to kill myself. I'm not going
to rob the the
Walmart."
Anyway, the ATF agent disarmed him. They
charged him with felon with a gun. It's
a mandatory minimum sentence of 8 years.
But, he got out on bail. And he used to
call me every single day and say, "I'm
going to kill myself. I'm going to kill
myself. I'm going to kill myself." And
I'd say, "James, you say this every day.
You're not going to kill yourself.
You're going to relax. You're going to
do what your attorney tells you to do."
I said, "Buddy, take a break. Fly out
here. I'm in DC." He was in Montana.
"Fly out here for a week or two and just
decompress and we can talk about
everything. You're going to get past it.
You're not going to get
fell in with a gun. You know, the the
the attorney's is going to argue, you
know, mental strain and
Well, on July 4th
of 2023,
his sister was lighting a firecracker
and it went off in her hand and it blew
two of her fingers off.
So, he calls me and he says, "My sister
had this accident with a firecracker.
She's in surgery now. They're trying to
sew her fingers back on."
And I said, "Oh my god, that's terrible.
I'll send flowers. Tell her, you know,
hope everything works out okay." And I
said, "But you sound awfully good." And
he said, "Yeah, I feel really good. I
feel really good about things." I said,
"Great. Great."
Two days later, his sister calls me and
I said, "Oh my god, how are you doing?"
She said, "I'm okay. It was a long
surgery. They reattached my fingers.
That's not why I'm calling." She said,
"James killed himself last night."
And I was like, "What?" I said, "Why
would he do that?"
I said, "I just talked to him two days
ago. He sounded great."
And she said, "He sounded great because
he had made up his mind to do it."
And he left a note.
And he said to his mother,
"Call John and tell him I said I was
sorry."
And I felt just like Pete Seeger felt
with Phil Ochs, you selfish bastard.
How could you do this?
I told you a thousand times, call me.
Call me if you're thinking of doing
something like that.
And he didn't.
He walked down to a neighbor's house,
strung up a noose in an oak tree, and he
hung himself.
And just like Pete said, I'll never
forgive him for doing that.
But anyway, things really do get better.
There are a thousand people out there
who want the best for you, and who are
willing to take a phone call and be a a
friendly ear.
Rely on the people around you. Rely on
your friends and family.
That's what I would say. Was there ever
a moment for you where you felt hopeless
and down in the dumps like that? Yeah,
the night that I got arrested. And my
And my wife talked me out of it.
I had five kids at home, too. What was
that moment like where you just where
just at that that moment your world was
coming crashing down on you? She
[snorts]
um we were watching TV the night of my
arrest and uh she said she said let's
let's go to bed. This has been a
terrible day. Let's just go to bed. And
I said, "No, you go to bed. I'm going to
watch some more TV." And I wasn't going
to watch TV. I was going to go down into
the garage and start the car and just
lay across the back seat.
And I think she suspected it.
And she said, "No,
let's go to bed."
And she stood there until I finally shut
off the TV and got up and and we went to
bed. And then you got arrested that
night? No, no, I got arrested that
morning. That's why I was so upset. Like
looking back knowing what you know now,
what would you have told your
self that day knowing what you know now?
You can tough this out. This is not
going to be as bad as you think it is.
In fact, my brother said something to me
the day of my arrest. He said, "I know
you can't see it,
but this is going to turn out to be the
best thing that ever happened to you."
And he was right.
As crazy as it sounds,
it was the best thing that ever happened
to me. You know, I think that people
they have this internal voice that's
telling them to do something. Whether
it's
to start a company, whether it's to
you know, break up with somebody,
whether it's to, you know, ask somebody
to marry them, whatever. And they don't
do it, and they don't do it. Like, what
do you think can happen to the person
that ignores their internal voice? Yeah.
And you know,
listen to that internal voice. Certainly
seek counsel from people you trust.
But listen to that internal voice. It's
important, right? It is. What do you
think? What is your overall
perspective of the world right now?
And what we're going through. I think
the world's in a very dangerous place
right now.
Very dangerous. You know, we've we've
got
the Russia-Ukraine war still, you know,
in a stalemate. Well, not really, the
Russians are winning, but
I mean, you'll they'll they'll fight for
weeks over 15 ft of territory.
Um we've got, you know, the US-Israeli
war against Iran, the opening and
closing and then reopening of the of the
Strait of Hormuz. Europe, yesterday I
saw breaking news, Europe has 6 weeks of
jet fuel left. It'll be an economic
calamity around the world if Europe runs
out of jet fuel.
Um in the meantime, the Chinese are
expanding by leaps and bounds. Here in
the United States, we're we're split
right down the center politically,
ideologically.
I mean, I
I've not seen anything like this,
certainly in my adult lifetime, but
I'm I'm just old enough to remember
1968, 1969. I was a kid.
Um
and things were as terrible then as they
are now. You know, Martin Luther King's
assassinated, then Bobby Kennedy's
assassinated, then Kent State, and then
the summer of love, and everybody's in
the street, and the cops are shooting
unarmed people, and
yeah. I think we're just as split now as
we were in '68 and '69. Do you think
that we're going to Do you think that
there's a bigger threat now for like
local acts of terrorism? Not
necessarily. I think what we have to be
worried about are
acts of lone wolf terrorism.
You know, somebody walking into a church
or a synagogue or a mosque and just
opening fire. You know, we've got What
is it? Like a mass shooting a day
according to the FBI's definition of a
mass shooting where three or more people
are injured. Every day.
I was I was giving an interview to a to
a Hungarian psychiatrist today. He's
doing a
a study on um on trauma.
And um
he told me that um he's interviewed
several FBI profilers who told him that
in the 1970s and the 1980s,
so the so-called golden age of serial
killers,
there was a point where there were 150
serial killers loose
killing.
Now,
on any given day, there are 30 serial
killers loose in America that we just
haven't caught yet.
And he And he said,
"You know, in Hungary, we can't even
fathom something like this because we've
never had a serial killer. Not a single
one."
And here in the United States, the first
documented serial killer began killing
in 1792.
That's crazy. I didn't know that. It's a
part of our culture. So, do you think
the What do you think the average person
can do? Cuz I think you're see some
people like, "Oh, you should just move
out of the country." Like, what can just
stay here and stay informed? For better
or for worse, we have to live and work
within the system that we've created for
ourselves.
And so, yeah, be as well informed as you
possibly can be, vote your conscience,
and then demand
change from your elected officials. They
work for us. And by God, if they don't
do what we tell them to do, then we've
got to throw them out and elect somebody
else. We have to take the system
seriously because it's the only system
that we have.